Okay today's דף *daf* is דף ל"ב *daf lamed bet* and we
start with a new פרק *perek* אלו נאמרים *Elu Ne'emarim*. I should
just say about the previous פרק *perek* we just did two points
going back. One is that the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* if you remember
spoke about the position of רבי Rebbe אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* that even
from a flying bird the man would divorce his wife and give
a כתובה *kesuvah* and רבי Rebbe יהושע Yehoshua. *Rabbi Yehoshua* said no
it had to be the people knitting in the sun in the
moon. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* tried to explain the whole thing having to
do with the earlier debate about what you need for testimony about
סתירה stira, *stira* about going into private but that was very hard
read from the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* if you remember and תוספות Tosafos,
*Tosafos* explains that actually they're having a completely different debate just about
there's no קינוי *kinuy* and סתירה *stira* there's just rumors and they're
really all talking about what type of rumors are enough that we
would advise the husband to divorce his wife but because there's no
basis he still has to give a כתובה *kesuvah*. Much easier read
of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. The other point is that if you
remember there's a discussion about when two witnesses one said she became
טמאה *temei'ah* and one said she didn't came at the same time
as opposed to coming one after the other. And רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
explains the same time to be תוך כדי דיבור dibur, *toch k'dei
dibbur* and so I alluded to the fact that that was only
רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*'s explanation. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says that actually only after
the first testimony is accepted by בית דין *beis din* and ruled
on then a second one that said she did not become טמאה
*temei'ah* would not have any weight. But if before there was any
ruling they were both in front of the בית דין *beis din*
that's when they would actually neutralize one another. So just two final
points about what we learned yesterday. Now we start a complete new
פרק *perek* and while it starts with a point about סוטה Sota,
*Sotah* this actually is a very important and broad פרק *perek* about
the reciting of texts halakhic reciting of texts and whether they have
to be in Hebrew or in another language. So let's take a
look. אלו נאמרים בכל לשון bechol lashon *Elu ne'emarim bechol lashon* the
following can be said in any language: פרשת סוטה Sota *Parshas Sotah*
so the פרשה parsha *parsha* of the סוטה *Sotah* which is interesting
even though he writes it in Hebrew and scrapes it into the
water but the actual recitation of saying to her you know if
a man did not sleep with you if a man did sleep
with you and she says אמן אמן *amen amen* that can all
be in translation. וידוי מעשר vidui ma'aser, *Viduy ma'aser* at the end
of three years a person has to say I have gotten rid
of all the backed-up מעשר ma'aser. *ma'aser* in my house and the
תורה Torah *Torah* gives a text for that. So here are two
cases where תורה Torah *Torah* actually is providing a formal text and
the tremendous חידוש *chiddush* is that you don't have to say it
exactly in the text the תורה Torah *Torah* provides you have to
say it in a translation but not in Hebrew. קריאת שמע Krias
Shema *Krias Shema* saying שמע Shema, *Shema* ותפילה *v'tefillah* and davenning mean
שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei *Shemoneh Esrei* וברכת המזון *u'Birkas HaMazon* ברכת המזון
*Birkas HaMazon* ושבועת העדות
ושבועת הפיקדון *u'shvuas ha'eidus u'shvuas hapikadon*. If somebody makes somebody testify take
an oath I impose upon you an oath that you should come
and testify for me if you saw and the person says I
take the oath I didn't see anything and he's lying he did
see something that could help this person in court then that person
would have to bring a קרבן *korban* for taking this false שבועת
העדות *shvuas ha'eidus*. שבועת הפיקדון *Shvuas hapikadon* is somebody says give me
back the object I lent you or you were watching for me
and he denies it and the original owner and the owner forces
him to take an oath and he takes an oath and he
is lying and then he admits it he also has to bring
a special קרבן *korban*. Both of those can be in any language.
And we'll see it's interesting because some of these like תפילה Tefillah
*tefillah* even if you think that תפילה tefillah *tefillah* is a biblical
and ברכת המזון *Birkas HaMazon* and these and these the oaths there's
no text given in the תורה Torah *Torah* so why would I
have actually thought they would have to be in Hebrew? And the
fact maybe I wouldn't have maybe that's just what the משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah* is teaching. But it is worth thinking about the fact that
is the חידוש *chiddush* that it can be in any language that
you don't have to do the text you know if the text
was given in Hebrew that is the text exactly as it was
given? Or maybe even if there was no text it just says
you thank God you bless God for the food maybe there's a
power of always using the Hebrew language even when there's no specified
text. But here it's telling you it doesn't apply at least to
these cases they can be in any language.
Now it's worth pausing and mentioning also oh let's just finish
this okay fine. So it's worth pausing and noting two תוספותים *Tosafosim*
here very important. One says אלו נאמרים בלשונם *elu ne'emarim bilshonam* so
take a look תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says ופירוש כל אדם בלשונו שהוא
שומע *u'peirush kol adam bilshono she'hu shomeia*. If you're not going to
say it in Hebrew you have to say it in a language
you understand. Interestingly the word שומע *shomeia* here means understand. לאפוקי למדיי
שאינו מלשון פרסי מאינו שומעו *L'afokei l'madai she'eino milashon parsi me'eino shomei'o*
you can't say it in a foreign language you don't understand. You
can say it in Hebrew if you don't understand it which is
also interesting. When do we say that texts require a degree of
כוונה *kavana* to be יצא *yotzei*? If you said all the right
words in Hebrew but didn't have any idea maybe you need a
general idea that's interesting to explore by every individual area of הלכה
Halacha, *halacha*. But תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says anyway clearly in translation it'll
only work if you understand it. אבל בכל לשון be-chol lashon. *Aval
bechol lashon* but then he concedes you know really משמע בין שומע
בין אינו שומע *mashma bein shomeia bein eino shomeia* וגמרא לא משמע
הכי *u'Gemara lo mashma hachi*. But he says, but you know, if
we're being honest, any language sounds like maybe you don't even have
to understand it at all, but the גמרא, Gemara and we'll see
the גמרא Gemara by שמע, shema seems to say that no, part
it's about understanding. But he raises this question about can you say
a text that's not in the original Hebrew, in a different language
and you don't even understand it? And maybe that's good for certain
things. You know, one thinks for example דאבנינג davenning you have to
know what you're saying or you know it doesn't count as דאבנינג
davenning just the reciting of a text.
Okay and then should we look at these next תוספות, Tosfos קריאת
שמע ותפילה? Krias Shema uTefillah? תוספות Tosfos says תימה, teima, there's a
whole list of other things that we need to know whether you
can say them in translation or not. אמאי, Amai, שיר, Shir, הלל—I'm
Hallel not saying הלל—וקידוש של שבת וברכת הפירות, and making ברכות brachos
before eating food, וברכת המצוות, uBirkas HaMitzvos, and making a ברכה bracha
before מצוות, mitzvos, and all of these can be said in other
languages, so why not list them? וליכא למימר דלא נקט אלא דאורייתא,
Vleika lmeimar dlo nakat ela dOraisa, maybe it's limiting itself to דאורייתא
dOraisa issues. תוספות Tosfos says you can't say that, because first of
all there's questions, תפילה tefillah is most likely דרבנן, dRabbanan, קריאת שמע
Kriyas Shema is דרבנן, dRabbanan, you know, קידוש Kiddush is a דאורייתא.
dOraisa. Okay
so then תוספות Tosafos says at the end, he says like this:
ונראה—three vnira lines from the bottom—דהני נאמרים בכל לשון אפילו אינו שומע
הילכך לא דמו להני דמתניתין דנאמרים דווקא בלשונם. dhani neemarim bechol lashon
afilu eino shomeia hilkach lo damu lhani dmasnisin dneemarim davka bilshonam. Okay
so he says that תוספות Tosafos now going back to his question
about whether you have to be able to understand it or
not, you know, תוספות Tosafos here says that the ones that he
is discussing here, ברכת הפירות, Birkas HaPeiros, ברכת המצוות, Birkas HaMitzvos, etc.,
that they can be said even if you don't understand. The משנה
Mishna you can say in translation if you do understand. These you
can say in a different language even if you don't understand. All
this is very confusing. Why should there be a split this way
and why should things like a ברכה bracha be something that you
can say without understanding? But anyway the point—the key is to see
that תוספות Tosafos is recognizing there are other things that are on
the list of translation, and the ongoing question of if they're in
a translation do you have—is it limited to cases when you understand
what you're saying? Now back to the משנה, Mishna okay? ואלו נאמרים
בלשון הקודש. Veilu neemarim bilshon hakodesh. The following must be in Hebrew:
מקרא ביכורים, Mikra Bikkurim, the recitation of ביכורים, Bikkurim, ארמי אובד אבי
Arami oved avi when the person brings the ביכורים, Bikkurim, which is
interesting you know because it's the basis of the הגדה Haggadah and
the הגדה Haggadah certainly is about understanding and discussing and you know
there's no limit—it doesn't have to be in Hebrew the הגדה, Haggadah,
but the actual מקרא ביכורים Mikra Bikkurim on which it's based, which
is also about giving praise to God, maybe we would allow person
to use his own language or at least his own, you know,
maybe translation, but they have to be the same words, but at
least in translation? No, that has to be exactly the way it
is—the way it is written. וחליצה, Vchalitzah, the taking off you know
of the shoe and the spitting, ככה יעשה לאיש kacha yeaseh laish
where the woman says you know this is what should be done
to the man, that has to be in Hebrew.
Now I should mention that just because it has to
be—that's how the recitation has to be done, it doesn't necessarily mean
that it would be invalid the חליצה chalitzah if you wouldn't do
it, separate question. ברכות וקללות, Brachos uklalos,
the blessings and the curses on הר גריזים והר עיבל, Har Gerizim
vHar Eival, now that's really not an ongoing הלכה, Halacha that's about
at the time they did it they had to do it in
Hebrew. And the reason actually it's mentioned as we'll see in a
minute in the משנה Mishna is because that serves as the basis
for learning these other things have to be in Hebrew. So even
though that's really just a historical event and not a הלכה Halacha,
or was a one-time הלכה, Halacha nevertheless it's being mentioned. ברכת כוהנים,
Birkas Kohanim, the ברכה bracha the כוהנים Kohanim give to the people,
you know,
יברכך השם וישמרך, yevarechecha Hashem veyishmerecha, וברכת כוהן גדול, uBirkas Kohen Gadol,
the ברכה bracha that the כוהן גדול Kohen Gadol makes on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur when he reads from the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah,
which is interesting, certainly not a דאורייתא, dOraisa, interesting that that's included.
ופרשת המלך, Uparshas hamelech, when the
the פרשה parsha of the king when he you know I think
it might have stopped recording so let's just go back quickly.
Okay, so ואלו נאמרים בלשון הקודש, Veilu neemarim bilshon hakodesh, מקרא ביכורים,
Mikra Bikkurim, the reading for ביכורים, Bikkurim, ארמי אובד אבי Arami oved
avi when you're bringing ביכורים, Bikkurim, וחליצה, vchalitzah, the חליצה chalitzah when
the woman says ככה יעשה לאיש kacha yeaseh laish and the shoe
and the spitting, ברכות וקללות, brachos uklalos, the ברכות brachos and קללות
klalos on הר גריזים והר עיבל, Har Gerizim vHar Eival, those have
to be in Hebrew. Now that's not a הלכה halachic ongoing, that
was a one-time thing, but the reason it was mentioned is because
that's going to be the basis for these other things. ברכת כוהנים,
Birkas Kohanim, the ברכה bracha that the כוהנים Kohanim make, יברכך השם
וישמרך yevarechecha Hashem veyishmerecha in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we do
it also in the שול shul on the רגל regel or ספרד
Sefard all the time, וברכת כוהן גדול, uBirkas Kohen Gadol, the ברכה
bracha the כוהן גדול Kohen Gadol makes on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
when he reads from the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, that certainly is
not a דאורייתא, dOraisa, interesting that that's included, ופרשת המלך, uParshas Hamelech,
the פרשה of the king when he reads הקהל Hakhel from the
ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, ופרשת עגלה ערופה, uParshas Eglah Arufah, you know
the—by the case—by the עגלה ערופה eglah arufah when the—when the elders
go out, you know, and they say ידינו לא שפכו את הדם
הזה, yadeinu lo shafchu es hadam hazeh, our hands not spilled this
blood, ומשוח מלחמה בשעה שמדבר אל העם, umoshuach milchamah beshaah shemedabeir el
haam,
and the anointed, the כוהן Kohen anointed for the war when he
speaks to the people and says if somebody's fearful he bought a
house, you know, just built a house, just married a wife, and
so on, which is really shocking because of all—at there's any time
when you think that you have to actually make sure that people
are understanding what you're saying and it's not really a r— ritual,
it's more about informing people, it would be that case of the,
of the משוח מלחמה, Mashuach Milchama, and nevertheless that has to be
in Hebrew. So it's going to be interesting where we learn about
that that some can be in translation or any language and some
can be in Hebrew. So now it says like this,
okay, מקרא ביכורים כיצד. Mikra Bikurim Keitzad. How do we know? We're
sort of like skipping all the ones that can be in any
language from the משנה. Mishna. It sounds like we're just going to
assume things can be in translation unless we know otherwise. So how
about the ones that have to be in Hebrew? How do you
know that מקרא ביכורים Mikra Bikurim has to be in Hebrew? כיצד?
Keitzad?
וענית ואמרת לפני ה' אלהיך. ve'anita ve'amarta lifnei Hashem elokecha. ולהלן הוא
אומר והנו הלוים ואמרו. ulehalan hu omer ve'anu haleviyim ve'amru. So by
ביכורים Bikurim it says that you shall respond and say before God,
and by the, by the ברכות וקללות brachos ukelalos on הר גריזים
והר עיבל Har Gerizim veHar Eival it says the לוים Levi'im shall
respond and say. So again וענית ואמרת, ve'anita ve'amarta, וענו ואמרו. ve'anu
ve'amru. It's the combination of those verbs. מה להלן בלשון הקודש, ma
lehalan belashon hakodesh, the same way we know that the ברכות וקללות
brachos ukelalos on הר גריזים והר עיבל Har Gerizim veHar Eival were
in Hebrew, אף כאן בלשון הקודש. af kan belashon hakodesh. So you
see this is why the משנה Mishnah, mentioned הר גריזים והר עיבל.
Har Gerizim veHar Eival. It's even going to elaborate on it because
that really serves as the basis for these other things. חליצה כיצד?
Chalitza Keitzad? How about the case of the חליצה Chalitza of the
shoe and the spitting with the brother-in-law? וענתה ואמרה. ve'aneta ve'amra. Again
וענתה ואמרה, ve'aneta ve'amra, וענו ואמרו. ve'anu ve'amru. That combination to respond
and say somehow is understood to be it has to be exactly
in that language. ולהלן הוא אומר והנו הלוים ואמרו. ulehalan hu omer
ve'anu haleviyim ve'amru. מה להלן בלשון הקודש, ma lehalan belashon hakodesh, the
same way by the לוים Levi'im and the the two mountains when
they crossed the the Jordan was and the blessings and the curses
was in Hebrew, אף כאן בלשון הקודש. af kan belashon hakodesh. רבי
יהודה אומר וענתה ואמרה ככה. Rabbi Yehuda omer ve'aneta ve'amra kacha. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you don't need here you don't need maybe
in other cases you do, but here you don't need the וענתה
ואמרה ve'aneta ve'amra and the connection to the ברכות וקללות. brachos ukelalos.
By חליצה Chalitza it says ככה יעשה לאיש, kacha ye'aseh la'ish, this
is what should be done to the man. But it also says
you can read it by ואמרה ככה, ve'amra kacha, she must say
thusly. It has to be exactly thus. עד שתאמר בלשון הזה. ad
shetomar balashon hazeh. Okay, now we get to so that's the cases
at least the first set of
them. Now let's take a look at the ברכות וקללות. brachos ukelalos.
That was mentioned first, but this is the basis for the two
that preceded them. Okay, so ברכות וקללות כיצד? brachos ukelalos keitzad? כיון
שעברו ישראל את הירדן. keivan she'avru Yisrael es haYarden. So once they
crossed the Jordan now it's just going to tell you this is
not just here to tell you how we know it was in
Hebrew. This is now going to describe to you the whole history
of this. Once they passed over the Jordan ובאו להר גריזים ולהר
עיבל, uva'u leHar Gerizim uleHar Eival,
they came to הר גריזים והר עיבל Har Gerizim veHar Eival שבשומרון
shebeShomron which is in the שומרון, Shomron, שבצד שכם shebetzad Shechem which
is alongside שכם, Shechem, שבצד אלוני מורה shebetzad elonei Moreh which is
near אלוני מורה. elonei Moreh. Very interesting it's giving you all these
geographic markers but the Torah gave you all those geographic markers. שנאמר
הלא המה בעבר הירדן. shene'emar halo heimah be'ever haYarden. Behold they are
on the other side of the Jordan. ולהלן הוא אומר ויעבר אברם
בארץ עד מקום שכם עד אלון מורה. ulehalan hu omer vaya'avor Avram
ba'aretz ad mekom Shechem ad elon Moreh. הלא המה בעבר הירדן
אחרי דרך מבוא השמש בארץ הכנעני הישב בערבה מול הגלגל אצל אלוני
מורה. halo heimah be'ever haYarden acharei derech mevo hashemesh be'eretz haKena'ani hayoshev
ba'aravah mul haGilgal etzel elonei Moreh. So by אלוני מורה. elonei Moreh.
ולהלן הוא אומר ויעבר אברם בארץ עד מקום שכם עד אלון מורה.
ulehalan hu omer vaya'avor Avram ba'aretz ad mekom Shechem ad elon Moreh.
אצל אלוני מורה, etzel elonei Moreh, I think anyway. And אברם Avram
passed passed until the place of שכם Shechem until אלון מורה. Elon
Moreh. So the אלון מורה Elon Moreh of הר גריזים והר עיבל
Har Gerizim veHar Eival where the Torah gave us a marker,
מה אלון מורה האמור להלן שכם אף אלון מורה האמור כאן שכם.
mah elon Moreh ha'amur lehalan Shechem af elon Moreh ha'amur kan Shechem.
So it was in שכם. Shechem. So that's how we know the
fact that the משנה Mishnah. says שכם. Shechem. In שכם Shechem we
know was in שומרון. Shomron. Okay, so that's the first part. שבשומרון
שבצד שכם. shebeShomron shebetzad Shechem. Now שבצד אלוני מורה shebetzad elonei Moreh
and that that is by אלוני מורה. elonei Moreh. Okay. אף אלון
מורה כאן שכם. af elon Moreh kan Shechem. ששה שבטים עלו. shisha
shevatim alu. Okay, so now we're going to describe how it took
place.
ששה שבטים עלו לראש הר גריזים וששה שבטים עלו לראש הר עיבל.
shisha shevatim alu lerosh Har Gerizim veshisha shevatim alu lerosh Har Eival.
Six went to top of הר גריזים, Har Gerizim, six went to
top of הר עיבל, Har Eival, right? Those on הר גריזים Har
Gerizim are for the ברכה, bracha, those on הר עיבל Har Eival
are for the קללה. kelala. Actually up until today it has always
been the case that the הר גריזים Har Gerizim has vegetation all
over the mountain, they're like right next to one another, and הר
עיבל Har Eival is completely desolate, which is probably exactly why the
Torah chose symbolically הר גריזים Har Gerizim for the ברכה bracha and
הר עיבל Har Eival for the קללה. kelala. So six tribes went
up on each one. והכהנים והלוים והארון עומדים למטה באמצע. vehakohanim vehaleviyim
veha'aron omdim lematah ba'emtza. And the כהנים kohanim and the לוים Levi'im
and the ארון aron were down in the middle between the two
mountains. הכהנים מקיפים את הארון. hakohanim mekifim es ha'aron. So the כהנים
kohanim would
surround
the ארון, aron, the inner like protective circle. והלוים את הכהנים. vehaleviyim
es hakohanim. And the לוים Levi'im would surround the כהנים. kohanim. So
that would be, you sort of understand like these concentric circles or
squares. וכל ישראל מכאן ומכאן. vechol Yisrael mikan umikan. And all the
rest of the Israelite people were on both sides, six six on
each mountain. שנאמר וכל ישראל וזקניו ושוטריו. shene'emar vechol Yisrael uzekanav veshotrav.
Now
there's both the Torah tells you to do it, which is in
דברים, Devarim, and then it tells you how they did it in
יהושע. Yehoshua. So we're going to quote פסוקים pesukim from both. So
here's a פסוק pasuk from יהושע. And all of Israel and their
elders and their and their officers ושופטיו veshofetav and the judges עומדים
מזה ומזה לארון, omdim mizeh umizeh la'aron, were on both sides of
the ארון aron on the opposite mountains. הפכו פניהם כלפי הר גריזים.
hafchu fneihem klapei Har Gerizim. Now the משנה Mishnah continues. הפכו פניהם
כלפי הר גריזים. hafchu fneihem klapei Har Gerizim. So the the Torah
interestingly when it speaks about the קללות וברכות kelalos uvrachos and it
says קללות וברכות, kelalos uvrachos, but it only gives the text of
the קללות. kelalos. ארור האיש, arur ha'ish, cursed be the man who
makes a graven image,
etc., etc. So here it says הפכו פניהם כלפי הר גריזים ופתחו
בברכה. hafchu fneihem klapei Har Gerizim upat'chu bivracha. But what's the ברכה?
bracha? So the ברכה bracha we assume is the reverse. Blessed is
is the man who doesn't do this. And we're going to assume,
you know, that the ברכות *brachos* are going to come first. ופתחו
בברכה *upatchu bivracha*. ברוך האיש אשר לא יעשה פסל ומסכה *Baruch haish
asher lo yaaseh pesel umasecha* blessed is the man who does not
make an a graven image. ואלו ואלו עונים אמן *veileh veileh onim
Amen*. Now, it's interesting, even though you had they were facing הר
גריזים *Har Gerizim* and saying the ברכה *bracha*, you know, it's not
like like only half of the
people
endorse, you know, and affirm, you know, this statement. Everybody says אמן
*Amen*. So even though it's sort of like, you know, they're sort
of the two mountains are to suggest like, you know, you have
two choices before you, חיים *chaim* and טוב *tov*. You have the
you have, you know, the choice of good and the choice of
evil. This, you know, this is good and that's evil, but the
אמן *Amen*, which is the affirmation of the people, is coming from
both of the mountains. Okay. עונים אמן *onim Amen*. הפכו פניהם כלפי
הר עיבל *hafchu pneihem klapei Har Eival* then they turned to הר
עיבל *Har Eival* ופתחו בקללה *upatchu biklala* and they open with a
קללה *klala*. ארור האיש אשר יעשה פסל ומסכה *Arur haish asher yaaseh
pesel umasecha*. ואלו ואלו עונים אמן *veileh veileh onim Amen*. So then
they say the curse and everybody says אמן *Amen*. עד שגומרים ברכות
וקללות *ad shegomrim brachos ukelalos*. So then they do ברכה *bracha*, קללה
*klala*, ברכה *bracha*, קללה *klala*, ברכה *bracha*, קללה *klala*. They don't do
all the ברכות *brachos* and then all the קללות *klalos*; they alternate,
which makes of course a lot of sense. You have this choice.
You can be ארור *arur* or you can be ברוך *baruch*. Okay.
ואחר כך הביאו את האבנים *veacharkach hevi'u es haavanim* then they brought
the stones ובנו את המזבח *uvanu es hamizbeiach* so there's actually a
little, you know, complicated here trying to figure out the relationship because
the תורה Torah *Torah* says that you should take stones and erect
these stones and, you know, cover them with plaster and write all
the words of the תורה Torah *Torah* and you shall build an
altar and you shall offer sacrifices on it,
but were those stones connected to the altar, not connected to the
altar? In the תורה Torah *Torah* account it looks like they weren't
connected, but let's see what the משנה *Mishna* says. והביאו את האבנים
ובנו מהן מזבח mizbeach, *vehevi'u es haavanim uvanu mehen mizbeiach* so it
seems like it's understanding that the stones were same stones used for
the altar. They took the stones, they built the altar וסדו בסיד
*vesadu vasid* and they plastered it over וכתבו עליהן את כל דברי
התורה בשבעים לשון *vechatvu aleihen es kol divrei haTorah beshivim lashon* and
then they, and so now if you look at,
and they wrote all the תורה Torah *Torah* in 70 languages, which
is very interesting considering this משנה *Mishna*, right? To some degree this
is an aside because they're telling you what happened around the ברכות
*brachos* and the קללות *klalos*, but, you know, could have stopped. They
didn't have to tell you about the altar and the stones. And
when they, and it says you write the תורה Torah *Torah*, לשון
שנאמר באר היטב be'er heitev *lashon sheneemar beier heiteiv* you should write
the words of this תורה *Torah* very clear, explicated well. So right
alongside the ברכות *brachos* and קללות *klalos*, which have to be in
Hebrew and לשון הקודש *Lashon Hakodesh* and have to be on the
basis for other things in לשון הקודש *Lashon Hakodesh*, is the idea
that the תורה *Torah* was written right at the very beginning with
70 translations. It should be accessible to all, which suggests more latitude
in saying things in translation. And we'll see about that in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know, the concept of whether the תורה *Torah*
was given in other languages. We'll see what that means. Okay. ונטלו
את האבנים *venatlu es haavanim* so then they apparently, so it sounds
strange, like, you know, you had this מזבח mizbeach. *mizbeiach* built with
the תורה *Torah* written all around the the stones of the מזבח
*mizbeiach* and the sacrifices offered up. A real coming together of this
עבודה avodah, *avoda* and תורה *Torah*, which is quite fascinating. And then
they dismantled, you know, the מזבח *mizbeiach*, they took the stones ובאו
ולנו במקומם *uvau velanu bimkomam* and they went and they slept in
their place and if you look רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says בגלגל *beGilgal*
that was in גלגל *Gilgal* and there they erected the stones, which
also gets a little confusing
because if you look in יהושע *Yehoshua* they took 12 stones from
the feet of the כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim* and it seems to be
a completely different thing to remember the idea of the crossing of
the ירדן Yarden *Yarden*
and that was erected in גלגל *Gilgal* in the first place where
they slept. So there seems to be somewhat of a conflation of
these things. Okay. So anyway, that, now you're asking yourself, what about
all the other cases in the משנה *Mishna* that have to be
in Hebrew? We only did the first three. So that's coming up.
That's in later משניות *Mishnayos*. Okay, but the משנה *Mishna* does not
bother to justify the things that could be in other languages. And
it could very well be because of this thing we just said,
that the תורה *Torah* was written in all these languages right when
they crossed the ירדן Yarden. *Yarden*. So if you want something to
be only in Hebrew, you know, then you need a פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* to tell you it has to be only in Hebrew. But
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to show how we can basis
for saying that these things can be, can be in other language,
that the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is going to sort of indicate that
they can be in other
language. פרשת סוטה מנלן menalan? *Parshat Sota minalan*? How do you know
סוטה *Sota* can be in another language? דכתיב dechativ, ואמר הכהן לאשה
*dechtiv veamar hakohein laisha* that the כהן kohen *kohein* shall say לאשה
*laisha* to the woman. So because it says לאשה *laisha*. Now רש"י
*Rashi* says it means he quotes a different פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*: ואמר
אל האשה *veamar el haisha*.
So to the woman, you know, which somehow means like, somehow that
she should understand it בכל לשון שהוא אומר bechol lashon shehu omer.
*bechol lashon shehu omer*. Now any language he says, but really it
would mean any language that she understands. Goes back, you know, first
רש"י *Rashi*, אל האשה משמע דברים הנכנסים בלבה *el haisha mashma devarim
hanichnasim belivah* right? The whole sense is to warn her and to
tell her the consequences. Haven't, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just
yesterday spoke about or a few days ago, whatever, spoke about all
the different ways in which, you know, different ways it's being recited
to inform what the waters are going to do, what the consequences
are and so on. You want her to understand this שמכרת בלשון
*shemakkeres belashon*. Okay. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan. *Tanu rabanan* we taught, משמיעין
אותה בכל לשון שהיא שומעת *mashmi'in osah bechol lashon shehi shoma'as* and
that's again תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos'* point that you have to understand.
You can you inform her in any language that she understands על
מה היא שותה al ma hi shosa, ובמה היא שותה uvma hi
shosa, *al mah hi shotah uvmah hi shotah*. שותה. You know, for
what is she drinking and in what is she drinking, על מה
נטמאת ובמה היא נטמאת, al ma nitmes uvma hi nitmes,
for what is she become tamei and with what she has become
tamei. Now what does all this mean? So let's take a look.
על מה al ma היא שותה, על עסקי קינוי וסתירה. al iskei
kinui usira. Why is she drinking? Why is this all happening? It's
happening because, you know, that's sort of like the formal halachic criteria.
You were warned and you were and there was סתירה, and this
sort of is why now under these circumstances that's when this process
takes place. ובמה היא שותה, what is she drinking with? במקדה של
חרס bemikdesha shel cheres in a type of a pottery, you know,
like a vessel, the water is in there, you know, because that's
sort of demeaning. So it's a little like mixed, like why are
those two על מה and במה, bama, what does drinking in this
type of pottery connect conceptually to the idea of like this halachic
criteria? Anyway, but those are, so you explain like this is symbolic
of like the bad acts that, you know, you did or you
were suspected of doing. על מה נטמאת, al ma nitmes, on what
did she become tamei? על עסקי שחוק וילדות. al iskei schok veyaldus.
Because, you know, what would have led to becoming tamei? What were
the things that would have brought this about? And now we're not
talking about halachic criteria, you're sort of giving her
like מוסר. mussar. You know, this comes from being too frivolous and
so on, and easily seduced. ובמה היא נטמאת, uvma hi nitmes, now
we're sort of back to halacha, בשוגג או במזיד באונס או ברצון.
beshogeg o bemeizid be'ones o beratzon.
Now it's important to know the circumstances. Were you forced? Was it
rape? Were you like somehow you thought that this was your husband
and it wasn't your husband? Some type of a thing like that.
So it's interesting, two of these are sort of more about מוסר
mussar and lessons and two are about halachic criteria. וכל כך למה?
vechol kach lama? שלא להוציא לעז על המים המרים. shelo lehotzi la'az
al hamayim hamarim. Now
why do we sort of spell all this out?
Now it's not all of this,
but at least some of it. The last part רש"י says in
particular that she shouldn't say, "Oh look, I had sex with another
man and it didn't do anything, so the whole thing is a
farce." So it says no, we want to make it clear to
her that, you know, there are some cases like שוגג shogeg and
אונס ones where because you weren't מזיד, meizid, willful and intentional, that
it's not going to test you, so you should not question the
efficacy of them. וידוי מעשר, vidui ma'aser the recitation of מעשר. ma'aser
מנלן? Menalan? דכתיב, dechativ: how do you know that can be in
other languages? דכתיב: ואמרת לפני ה' אלהיך בערתי הקדש מן הבית. ve'amarta
lifnei Hashem elokecha biarti hakodesh min habayis. Okay, I have destroyed the
whole say, meaning got rid of it, distributed the מעשר from my
house.
ויליף אמירה מסוטה. veyalif amira miSota. Okay, and it's by סוטה, ואמר
הכהן אל האשה, ve'amar hakohen el ha'isha, רש"י says anyway, here's ואמרת,
ve'amarta, so anytime it says אמר, amar, אמר amar is seen as
word generic, you communicate this idea. Okay, maybe דיבור, maybe וענו ואמרו,
ve'anu ve'amru, using two verbs is a specific text. But ואמרת ve'amarta
is, get this idea across, so therefore it doesn't have to be
exactly this text. Okay, does raise an interesting question, right, about all
of these, especially if you think about how the גמרא Gemara before
just sort of gave all these things that the כהן kohen were
saying that are not in the פסוקים. pesukim. The פסוקים pesukim have
just said, you know, a very clear text. What is, is it
does it have to be a translation or can it be like
the gist of this? Like קריאת שמע Krias Shema. had to be
a translation, right? But something like this, if you say the gist
but you don't say a translation, does that also work? Not clear.
Okay. בערתי הקדש. biarti hakodesh. ויליף
אמירה מסוטה, veyalif amira miSota, בכל לשון שהוא אומר. אמר ליה רזבילא
לאביי, amar lei Razvila le'Abaye, רזבילא Razvila said to אביי: Abaye: וליליף
אמירה מלוים. veleilif amira miLevi'im. מה להלן בלשון הקדש אף כאן בלשון
הקדש. ma lehalan bilshon hakodesh af kan bilshon hakodesh. I know notes
by לויים Levi'im also וענו הלוים ואמרו, ve'anu haLevi'im ve'amru, and here
it says ואמרת, ve'amarta,
okay? So no, דנין אמירה גרידתא מאמירה גרידתא. danin amira gerideta me'amira
gerideta. So this is what we said, in both cases by the
סוטה and by the וידוי מעשר vidui ma'aser. it just says אמירה
amira without another verb. ואין דנין אמירה גרידתא מענייה ואמירה, ve'ein danin
amira gerideta me'aniya ve'amira, but by this as a soul אמירה amira
and you don't learn it out from ענייה ואמירה aniya ve'amira that
you have by
הלוים. haLevi'im. תני, tani, רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי אומר: Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai omer: אומר אדם שבחו בקול נמוך
וגנותו בקול רם. omer adam shvacho bekol namuch ugnuso bekol ram. A
person says his, you know, goes around and
talks praises himself, you should not say your, you know, speak about
your own praises, and if you're going to speak about them, it
should be in an undertone. Don't go around telling everybody how wonderful
you are. וגנותו בקול רם, ugnuso bekol ram, but if you want
to tell people your faults, that you feel free to publicize that.
Now that's a little funny, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara
does with that. שבחו בקול נמוך מוידוי מעשר, shvacho bekol namuch mividui
ma'aser, your praise in a low voice from וידוי מעשר. vidui ma'aser,
Because by וידוי מעשר, vidui ma'aser
וידוי מעשר is really your praising yourself. I did this right, I
did this right, I did this right, עשיתי ככל אשר צויתני השקיפה
ממעון קדשך. asisi kechol asher tzivisani hashkifa mimon kodshecha. You're going in
and announcing, look at all these things I did right. So but
that you don't make a big announcement, you say it. It doesn't
say וענו ואמרו, ve'anu ve'amru, which sounds like announce, so another point
not exactly the לשון הקדש leshon hakodesh point, but the simple, just
say it. Okay, you have to say it, you say it, don't
go ahead make a big announcement. Okay, that's how you know that.
גנותו. gnuso. גנות בקול רם, gnus bekol ram, but if you're going
to talk about things you did wrong, that you can go ahead
and announce. ממיקרא ביכורים, Mi Mikra Bikkurim, from מקרא ביכורים. Mikra Bikkurim.
Now מקרא ביכורים Mikra Bikkurim is not, how's that גנות gnus though?
Because ארמי אובד אבי, Arami oveid avi, because you start by, you
start, that's like what we learned by פסח, Pesach, it says מתחיל
בגנות, matchil bignus, the same word of גנות, gnus, that
לבן Lavan if it's about לבן, Lavan, that לבן Lavan wanted to
destroy us as a רשע rasha and he's related and wanted to
kill us and it's telling bad things, not bad things that you
did something wrong, but things that are like a little bit like
not a happy part of your story. Okay, so now why still
why should you go ahead and say those things loudly? So the
גמרא Gemara says,
where are we, מקרא ביכורים, Mikra Bikkurim, וגנותו בקול רם. ugnuso bekol
ram. So it says first of all, is that really true that
you're supposed to go ahead and make announcements of things that are
like don't reflect well on you or
embarrassing things? ואמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי מפני מה
תיקנו תפילה בלחש? Va'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai mipnei
ma tiknu tefillah belachash? Why is שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei in an
undertone? Now yes, we learned it from חנה, Chana, but nevertheless it's
like if you look at רש"י, מפני מה תיקנו שיהא אדם אומר
תפילתו בלחש כשדאשכחן בחנה וקולה לא ישמע. mipnei ma tiknu sheyei adam
omer tefillaso belachash kideashchan beChana vekolah lo yishama.
So חנה Chana we see that it was an undertone, but okay,
why did חז"ל Chazal choose to follow this model? כדי שלא לבייש
את עוברי עבירה, Kedei shelo levayesh es ovrei aveirah, in order not
to embarrass people that did sins because now because you maybe in
your דאבנינג davening to השם Hashem you want to talk about what
you've done wrong and you really want to have an honest conversation
with God and if you have to say it out loud, you'll
be afraid and this makes it very intimate and private and you
can be honest with your faults and with your sins. So because
you are saying it quietly. שהרי לא חילק הכתוב מקום בין חטאת
לעולה. Sheharei lo chilek haksav makom bein chatas le'olah. So
and we see this because looking at a different place of עבודה,
the קרבנות, korbanos, that when you would bring a חטאת chatas and
an עולה olah they would both be slaughtered in the north. So
nobody would know, you give your sheep to a כהן kohen and
somebody else would give their sheep to a כהן kohen and presumably
I don't know maybe they look different people could tell whose was
whose, and if they were in different places, somebody would say, oh,
yours is being שחט'ד shechted in the חטאת chatas place, you did
a sin. But since they're both being שחט'ד shechted to the north
of the מזבח, nobody knows whether yours is a חטאת chatas or
an עולה. olah. So if you want to be talk about your
sins to God, it's between you and God, it's nobody else's business.
So here the גמרא Gemara particularly focuses on a sense of like
sin,
לא תימא גנותו אלא משום צערא, lo seima gnus o ella mishum
tza'ara, and that was part of the problem about the whole thing
of ארמי אובד אבי, Arami oveid avi, like it wasn't sinful, it
might not have been the most illustrious time of our history, okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, you're right, I don't really mean
that, we merely mean your like when you're distressed, your pain, that
you should tell people about. כדתניא וטמא טמא יקרא, Kedisanya vetamei tamei
yikra,
that the מצורע metzora is sent out of the camp and he
has to say I'm טמא, tamei, I'm טמא, tamei, צריך להודיע צערו
לרבים ורבים מבקשים עליו רחמים. tzarich lehodi'a tza'aro lerabbim verabbim mevakshim alav
rachamim. He has to tell people that he's in pain and people
could pray for him and this is really very important because people
don't, a lot of people are suffering and they're afraid to bother
anybody with their suffering, to say anything to anybody, to say that
they're in pain. I don't want to trouble the person, it'll make
them look weak, they have to put on a good front, and
it's actually very powerful
pastoral psychological point about how people should let people know when they're
suffering so people can actually help them. So to some degree that's
ארמי אובד אבי, Arami oveid avi, we had like less than illustrious
startings, I don't know exactly how that's exactly the same, but some
people like maybe feel
sorry feel want to help you if there thing something like that
is a bad story about you. It's a little bizarre again the
parallel because it ends the story ends good right now not in
pain. But anyway. Okay. וכל מי שאירע בו דבר צריך להודיע לרבים
ורבים מבקשים עליו רחמים. Vechol mi she'ira bo davar tzarich lehodi'a lerabbim
verabbim mevakshim alav rachamim.
Okay.
So that is true in any time when something happens that you
have to tell people and people will come and they'll pray for
you or they'll come to your aid. גופא, Gufa, אמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי מפני מה תיקנו תפילה בלחש? amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai mipnei ma tiknu tefillah belachash? Why
is תפילה in an undertone? שלא לבייש את עוברי עבירה. Shelo levayesh
es ovrei aveirah. For people who did sins. Now also what's interesting
about this is it just makes it just assumes that people will
be adding their own words into שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and not
just saying the words of the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei. itself. You're
allowed to add words but nobody does it nowadays even though or
people should, but it's all become this ritual text that we recite.
And here very powerful, prayers בכל לשון and we're actually saying that
it was structured in this way to be in an undertone to
encourage people or to make it possible for people to have their
conversations to God in this שמונה עשרה. שהרי לא חילק הכתוב מקום
בין חטאת לעולה. Sheharei lo chilek haksav makom bein chatas le'olah. Okay,
no difference between where the חטאת chatas and עולה olah they're both
in the north. והלא איכא דמים. Vehalo ika damim. What do you
mean? But the blood is in a different place. So you could
see that
way whether the blood goes up on the top which is a
חטאת chatas or in the bottom which is an עולה. olah. דם
חטאת למעלה, Dam chatas lemala, the דם dam of a חטאת chatas
is put on the horns at the top, ודם עולה למטה, vedam
olah lemata, and the blood of an עולה olah is thrown on
the walls of the מזבח. So the גמרא Gemara gives the obvious
answer: התם כהן הוא דידע. hasam kohen hu deyada. So fine, I
mean the כהן kohen knows, oh, this is
ראובן's Reuven from ראובן's... Reuven All they see is blood, but when
they see you give your animals to the כהנים, they might be
able, I mean it's a little bizarre and תוספות Tosafot actually says,
like since when do we assume people are sort of paying attention
and can recognize, you know, whose animal or whatever, but anyway, but
that at least is something that they'll say, oh wasn't that that
animal you just gave, that black one with the spots or whatever
and then they'll see where it's being brought. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. והא איכא חטאת נקבה ועולה זכר? Ve-ha
ika chatas nikeva ve-olah zachar? As the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
a חטאת chatas has to be a female sheep or goat, and
an עולה olah has to be male, and therefore you can, you'll
see, so somebody will see did you give a כהן a female
or a male? תוספות also says like are people really paying attention
to that? But presumably yes. Okay, especially if you're waiting around for
your turn and maybe you have nothing better to do. But anyway,
חסוי מחסיא באליה. Hasuy mechasya be-alyah. No, no, no.
You won't be able to see the genitals because sheep have this
fat tail, so people won't be able to tell which is a
male or female sheep. It's interesting, makes, I mean I'm not a
farmer, I have no idea, but I would imagine in most species,
you know, there're differences in the animals besides just their genitalia, but
the גמרא Gemara says fine, people will not be able to tell
by a casual looking that it's male or female sheep. So the
גמרא Gemara says תינח כבשה שעירה מאי איכא למימר? Tenach kivsa seira
mai ika lemeimar? Fine if you're giving a sheep, but what if
you're giving a goat? You can give goat for a חטאת chatas
or an עולה, olah, and then there's no fat tail and you
could tell. התם איהו דקמיכסיף נפשיה. Hasam ihu de-kamichsif nafshei.
There you're embarrassing yourself, he embarrassed himself. איבעי ליה לאתויי כבשה וקמייתי
שעירה. Ibei lei le-asuyei kivsa ve-ka-maisei seira. He could have brought a
sheep and he brought a goat, so the תורה makes it possible
for you to not have to publicize, you know, what you're doing.
You can, if you bring a sheep, nobody will know whether you're
bringing a חטאת chatas or עולה. olah. If you for whatever reason
want to bring a goat then that's you did that for, you
did that to yourself. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says חטאת עבודה
זרה דלא סגיא דלאו שעירה מאי איכא למימר? Chatas avodah zarah dela
sagya delav seira mai ika lemeimar? How about a חטאת chatas for
a, for the sin of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? That can only
be a goat, so that will be a sin that people will
tell, you have no choice and it's obvious that you have now
done a sin because you're bringing a שעירה seira and people will
see that you're bringing a, you know, a female animal, so they'll
know it was a חטאת. chatas. התם נכסוף וניחסי כי היכי דנתכפר
ליה. Hasam nichsof ve-nechsi ki heichi de-niskapar lei. No, no, no. That's
about עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. עבודה זרה, Avodah zarah, you know what?
A little extra embarrassment maybe is appropriate because you need something more
to achieve atonement. Okay. So that was a fascinating discussion about, you
know, about
תפילה
and your own words, which very much fits with this whole discussion
here about בכל לשון. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. קריאת שמע. Krias Shema קריאת שמע Krias Shema can be
in any language. מנלן? How do you know this? דכתיב שמע ישראל,
De-ksiv Shema Yisrael, hear O Israel, בכל לשון שאתה שומע, be-chol lashon
she-ata shomea, hear means however you understand it.
Now
by the way, the גמרא Gemara here is quoting פסוקים psukim and
the simple sense of this גמרא is absolutely that קריאת שמע Krias
Shema at least the first פסוק pasuk or the first paragraph is
דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, which is a lot of other גמרות Gemoras as well,
but תוספות has a long תוספות here says but you know there
are some גמרות Gemoras that sound like it's דרבנן. de-Rabbanan. So there's
actually not a good resolution or clear position that emerges from the
סתם stam of the גמרא whether קריאת שמע shema, is דאורייתא de-Oraisa
or דרבנן, de-Rabbanan, but this one certainly assumes it's דאורייתא. de-Oraisa. Okay.
תנו רבנן. קריאת שמע ככתבה. Krias Shema ki-ksava. You have to read
it exactly as it is written. דברי רבי. Divrei Rabbi. That's what
Rabbi says, so it cannot be in other languages. וחכמים אומרים בכל
לשון. Vachachamim omrim be-chol lashon. No,
it can be in other languages. מאי טעמא דרבי? Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi?
What's the reason of Rabbi? אמר קרא והיו בהווייתן יהו. Amar kra
ve-hayu be-havayasan yehu. It says these words shall be, you know, והיו
הדברים האלה על לבבך, ve-hayu hadevarim ha-eileh al levavecha, they should be
on your heart, so they should be exactly as they were given.
Sort of like the ככה kacha before in the משנה. It has
to be in the Hebrew, in the original. ורבנן אמר קרא שמע
בכל לשון שאתה שומע. Ve-Rabbanan amar kra shema be-chol lashon she-ata shomea.
Okay,
we're going to emphasize שמע shema? here, that it's about understanding, and
understanding means that it can be in any language. ורבנן נמי הא
כתיב והיו? Ve-Rabbanan nami ha ksiv ve-hayu? What do the Rabbis do
with והיו? ve-hayu? Again, somehow assumes that it has to be telling
you something הלכה halacha and not just the meaning of the פסוק
itself. So what is that demanding? ההוא שלא יקרא למפריע. Hahu shelo
yikra lamafreia. It has to be in the right order. You can't
read the פסוקים psukim out of order. Okay, there has to be,
you know, it has to follow, the words have to,
the sentences have to be each sentence has to be in its
own order and the sentences have to be in order relative to
one another, but it does not, it's not, it doesn't have to
be in Hebrew. Okay. ורבי שלא יקרא למפריע מנא ליה? Ve-Rabbi shelo
yikra lamafreia mena lei? Where does Rabbi know that you can't, you
that it's not good if you did it out of order? נפקא
ליה מדברים הדברים. Nafka lei midevarim hadevarim. It says והיו הדברים האלה,
ve-hayu hadevarim ha-eileh, these things. He could have just said והיו דברים
האלה. ve-hayu devarim ha-eileh. Of course that would mean something different. But
anyway, the extra ה hei means it has to be exactly like
this, it has to be in Hebrew and it has to be
in this order. ורבנן דברים הדברים לא משמע להו. Ve-Rabbanan devarim hadevarim
lo mashma lehu.
They're not going to make a big deal about the extra ה,
hei, and it's not even so extra. Okay, so therefore they emphasize
שמע, Shma any language, and Rabbi והיו, ve-hayu, that it has to
be in Hebrew. ורבי נמי הא כתיב שמע? Ve-Rabbi nami ha ksiv
shema? What does Rabbi do with שמע? Shma ההוא מיבעי ליה להשמיע
אזנך מה שאתה מוציא מפיך. Hahu mibaei lei lehashmia oznecha mah she-ata
motzi mi-picha. That,
let your ears hear what you is coming out of your mouth.
Like, you know, it's sort of like a phrase, like, do you
hear what— or like exactly what you are saying? Are you hearing
what you are saying right now? Anyway, but what it technically means
is, is that for it to count as speech, it has to
be you have to be able to hear it. Okay, it's not
like you say it so softly that it's inaudible. And this is
an interesting requirement in general about הלכה about, you know, things require
speech, is it does it have to be audible, audible to you,
audible to anybody, etc. But here by שמע Shma רבי Rebbe, is
saying that that means that it has to be audible. Okay. ורבנן
סברי ליה כמאן דאמר הקורא את שמע ולא השמיע לאזנו יצא V'Rabbanan
savri leh k'man d'amar hakore es Shma v'lo hishmia l'ozno yatza and
the Rabbis hold, no, I could hold that you actually are יוצא
yotse with it, you know, even if it— excuse me, הקורא את
שמע ולא השמיע לאזנו יצא, hakore es Shma v'lo hishmia l'ozno yatza,
yes, and even if you do not hear it, you are יוצא.
yotse. So the, so the Rabbis are lenient in both ways. They
both say that it can be in other languages, that's what שמע
Shma tells you, and שמע Shma, also say— because it means other
languages, it doesn't demand that it be audible.
So combining those two leniencies and רבי Rebbe is strict in both,
you could imagine ways in which you could have said, you know,
if you emphasize the formal text like רבי, Rebbe maybe hearing it
isn't as important, you know, and, you know, because it's all about
the, the formal text, whereas the Rabbis that allowed translations, maybe they
should דווקא davka demand hearing it. So it would be possible, and
תוספות discuss some of those possibilities. Okay, let's just do a little
bit more here to the get to the end of שמע Shma
and get to the larger theme about this idea of other languages
and, so, לימא קסבר רבי כל התורה בכל
לשון נאמרה? Leima kasavar Rebbe kol haTorah b'chol lashon ne'emra? Let's say
that רבי Rebbe holds that the entire תורה was said in all
languages. Okay, now what does this exactly mean? Well for, the simplest
sort of explanation, working explanation here of what it clearly means is
that when there are things, this is sort of what the תוספות
שאנץ Tosafot Shantz says, when there are things that the תורה demands
be recited, is the default to assume any language or is the
default to assume, you know, only Hebrew? When the תורה was given
in, you know, בכל לשון נאמרה b'chol lashon ne'emra was said, meaning
it was— meaning that the sayings in the תורה were, were from
the very outset assumed they could be said in all languages. Okay,
so let's just read it like that. Is the default all languages
or not? So כל התורה בכל לשון נאמרה. kol haTorah b'chol lashon
ne'emra. So presumably רבי Rebbe you have to assume that רבי Rebbe
would say the normal default is all languages. דאי סלקא דעתך בלשון
הקודש נאמרה, D'ee salka dachshach b'lashon hakodesh ne'emra, if the normal default
for רבי Rebbe is that we assume only Hebrew, והיו דכתב רחמנא
למה לי? v'hayu d'chasav rachmana lama li? Why would he have to
learn out from והיו v'hayu that it has to be in Hebrew?
That seems like the default is it could be any language. So
גמרא says no, איצטריך משום דכתיב שמע. itztrich mishum d'chativ Shma. No,
no, because it says שמע, Shma which could have suggested, you know,
maybe רבי Rebbe holds the default is Hebrew, but since שמע Shma
could have suggested other language, והיו v'hayu is to tell you no,
no, this is just like the normal rule, the normal rule is
Hebrew. Okay. So it's interesting, right, that רבי says Hebrew, but he
learned it from a פסוק, maybe we should infer that the normal
rule is, is any language, and it says no, no, the normal
rule could be Hebrew here for רבי too, but you know you
still needed the פסוק to emphasize that. And now we're going to
say the reverse for the Rabbis. לימא קסבר רבנן כל התורה בלשון
הקודש נאמרה? Leima kasavar Rabbanan kol haTorah b'lashon hakodesh ne'emra? Let's say
the Rabbis who say any language, maybe they say that the general
rule is Hebrew. דאי סלקא דעתך בכל לשון, d'ee salka dachshach b'chol
lashon,
because if they were to say that it could be in, the
general rule is any language, שמע דכתב רחמנא למה לי? Shma d'chasav
rachmana lama li? Why would you need שמע to tell you that
it can be in any language? That's the general rule. So גמרא
says איצטריך משום דכתיב והיו. itztrich mishum d'chativ v'hayu. No,
it would still be needed because it says והיו, v'hayu, so meaning
it could be that the rule is any language, but I need
שמע to tell you that rule is true here as well, so
you shouldn't be misled by the והיו v'hayu to think that this
is an exception to the rule. Okay, so the easiest way to
understand תורה בכל לשון נאמרה Torah b'chol lashon ne'emra or not, right,
is whether, as I said, it is when the תורה gives texts
is it assumed that— what is the rule? Is the rule any
language or is the rule Hebrew? Now clearly,
you know, there is a, it doesn't mean that all languages are
equivalent. The very fact that when there's a limiting word we sort
of say only Hebrew means even if the general rule is all
languages, those still sort of fall into a category of translation. And
that by the way does fit very well with the idea of
the שבעים לשון באר היטב, shivim lashon be'er heitev, an explanation. So
it's very powerful in the משנה, right, that תורה is given in
Hebrew but you cross the ירדן and the first thing you do
is you write it in all different languages, which is like כל
התורה כולה בכל לשון נאמרה. kol haTorah kulla b'chol lashon ne'emra. There
is available alternate languages to say things that need to be said.
So and that is I think a very powerful way to understand
exactly what's going on in the משנה. רש"י and תוספות speak about
reading from a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, maybe there are פרשיות parshiyot
that have to be read from the תורה itself, פרשת זכור, Parshat
Zachor, or maybe it just means whether ספר תורה sefer Torah itself
can be written in another languages, which we know is a debate,
but it doesn't exactly sound that way. Whether ספר תורה sefer Torah
can be written in other languages the, you know, is a question
about a ספר תורה sefer Torah and is whether it's written in
other languages. This seems like it's saying something else, whether fundamentally the
תורה allowed for alternate, for allowed for translations, which is suggested by
the משנה by the באר היטב when they crossed the ירדן.